Guide to the Raymond Laurel Lindeman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Raymond Laurel Lindeman papers
1929-1942
1938-1942
MS 815
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
The papers consist of correspondence, ecological writings, and research materials of Raymond L. Lindeman. The correspondence concerns his research work and publications. His writings and research are primarily devoted to the limnology of Cedar Creek Bog and Cedar Bog Lake in Anoka County, Minnesota. Also included are miscellaneous notes, essays and drawings by his wife, Eleanor Hall Lindeman.
Lindeman, Raymond Laurel, 1915-1942
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of G. Evelyn Hutchinson in 1971 and 1973; transferred from School of Forestry, 1999.
Scope and Contents
The Raymond L. Lindeman Papers consist of 3.5 linear feet of correspondence, ecological writings, research notebooks and other research materials. Miscellaneous notes, essays and drawings by his wife, Eleanor Hall Lindeman, are also included.
The correspondence mainly concerns Lindeman's research, publications and institutional employers. A number of letters concern the initial rejection and eventual acceptance of Lindeman's article "The Trophic Dynamic Aspect of Ecology" by Ecology Magazine. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by individual or organization.
The writings are mainly concerned with the limnology of Cedar Creek Bog and Cedar Bog Lake in northern Anoka County, Minnesota. They are arranged chronologically.
Notebooks and other research materials, which include photographs, charts and maps, follow the writings.
The Raymond L. Lindeman Papers were given to Yale University Library by G. Evelyn Hutchinson in 1971.
Biographical / Historical
Raymond L. Lindeman received his Ph.D. from the University of Minnesota in 1941. He was a post-doctoral fellow at Yale associated with Professor G. Evelyn Hutchinson when he died in June 1942, His paper, "The Trophic-dynamic Aspect of Ecology," published posthumously by Ecology Magazine, is considered a classic in the field of environmental science.
LIST OF CORRESPONDENTS
Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, 1942
W. C. Allee, 1941
American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1939
American College Bureau, 1941
American-Scandinavian Foundation, 1940
Jay D. Andrews, [n.d.]
Russell Artist, 1941
Tom Austin, 1940-41
James E. Ackert, 1938-39
Elbert H. Ahlstrom, 1939-41
American-Midland Naturalist (Theodore Just), 1939-42
George Banta Publishing Co., 1939
Leonard M. Bennetch, 1941
Clifford O. Berg, 1942
L. R. Betty, 1942
Bibliofilm Service, [n.d.]
Biological Abstracts, [n.d.]
Irving H. Blake, 1942
P. Blakiston's and Son and Co., Inc., 1938
M. W. Boesel, 1942
W. H. Bradley, 1939
Walter Breckenridge, 1941
Murray C. Buell, 1938-42
Stanley Cain, 1941
Ken Carlander, 1941
T. C. Carter, 1939
William Castle, 1941
Brother H. Charles, 1941
E. P. Cheatem, 1942
R. O. Christianson, 1939
E. B. Clarke, [n.d.]
W. A. Clemens, 1941-42
Paul S. Conger, 1939
Connecticut State Library, 1942
Cornell University Agric. Exp. Station, 1942
Glenn C. Couch, 1939
Cranbrook Press, 1942
Bill T. Crawford, 1941
Robert S. Campbell, 1939, 1941
J. Richard Carpenter, 1940-42
William S. Cooper, 1941-42
Kenneth E. Damonn, 1942
Robert A. Darrow, 1942
Charlotte Dawley, 1942
Edward S. Deevey, Jr., 1939-42
Ecological Monographs, 1941-42
W. T. Edmondson, 1939, 1941
C. J. Elmore, 1939
Arnold B. Erickson, 1939
Ecological Society of America, 1939-41
Ecology Magazine (Thomas Park), 1941-42
Samuel Eddy, 1936-37, 1941-42
Frank E. Eggleton, 1939-41
Merlin Findlay, 1939-41
Ray C. Friesner, 1940
T. H. Frison, 1938, 1940
Ira N. Gabrielson, 1941
Gamma Alpha, 1938
Brother George, 1941
W. M. Gersbacher, 1939
Gordon Ginther, 1938
Howard K. Gloyd, 1942
Brother H. Gregory, 1941
A. A. Granovsky, 1936, 1938-39
William J. K. Harkness, 1939, 1942
B. B. Harris, 1942
Fred Haynes, 1942
Harold J. Heady, 1941
Archie D. Hess, 1942
Willis G. Hewatt, 1939, 1942
Malcolm Higgins, 1938, 1940
Alec Hodson, 1941
Carl E. Hoffman, 1940
A. M. Holmquist, 1936-37
Carl L. Hubbs, 1939, 1941-42
A. G. Huntsman, 1939, 1942
Frank Hooper, 1941-42
G. Evelyn Hutchinson, 1940-41
Paul Illg, [n.d.]
William Ingram, 1941
Indiana Conservation Dept., 1939
A. P. Jacot, 1940-41
Jefferson Hotel, 1941
Minna E. Jewell, 1939
Paul Johnson, 1939
Vincent Jones, 1938
Chancey Juday, 1940-41
Ersal W. Kindall, 1939
Trevor Kincaid, 1940-42
Herbert Knutson, 1942
Walter C. Kraatz, 1942
Paul E. Kuehne, 1942
James B. Lackey, 1939, 1942
Carl F. Lagler, 1942
Charles Lavers, 1939-41
Limnological Society of America (Paul S. Welch), 1938-40
Arthur W. Lindquist, 1942
John H. Lockhead, 1942
Donald Lawrence, 1939, 1941-42
J. G. Mackin, 1940
James McLeod, 1940
MacMillan Co., 1939
J. Marr, 1942
Ruth Marshall, 1941
C. W. Metz, 1942
Clarence E. Michel, 1941-42
Lorus J. Milne, 1942
Minnesota Academy of Science, 1940
John Moyle, 1941
Frank J. Myers, 1939, 1941
Dwight E. Minnich, 1936, 1938-39, 1941-42
Walter G. Moore, 1940-42
National Academy of Sciences, 1941
G. Morley Neal, 1939
S. L. Neave, 1939
James G. Needham, 1941
Paul R. Needham, 1939
Thurlow C. Nelson, 1939
Newburg Photo Studios, 1941
C. L. Newcombe, 1942
National Research Council, 1940, 1942
Maurice C. Old, 1939
Theodore A. Olson, 1942
C. J. Ostenburg, 1939
Henry J. Ousting, 1936
Park, 1941
Robert W. Pennak, 1939
Larry Perrin, 1941
Philadelphia Academy of Science, 1941
Frank A. Pitelka, 1941
H. W. Popp, 1941-42
J. E. Potzger, 1941-42
D. A. Preston, 1941
G. P. Putnam, 1940
Ruth Patrick, 1941-42
G. W. Prescott, 1937, 1939, 1941-42
D. S. Rawson, 1939
G. B. Rigg, 1941
Gordon A. Riley, 1939
William A. Riley, 1942
Hugo S. Rodeck, 1939, 1942
Eugene W. Roelofs, 1941
Mary Dora Rogick, 1939, 1942
C. O. Rosendahl, 1940
Harold Russell, 1938
George Rysgaard, 1939
Chuck Reif, 1938, 1940-42
Victor E. F. Salmon, 1939
W. F. Sanders, 1942
M. B. Scotland, [n.d.]
M. W. Senstius, 1941
V. E. Shelford, 1942
H. H. Shoemaker, 1942
Sigma Xi Society, 1939, 1941
Harry S. Smith, 1941
Lloyd L. Smith, 1939, 1941-42
J. Dewey Soper, 1941-42
Stanford University Press, 1938
Frank A. Stromsten, 1939
H. V. Sverdrup, 1941
Gustav Swanson, 1940
H. S. Swingle, 1941-42
Paul B. Sears, 1939, 1941-42
Clarence E. Taft, 1939, 1942
Horace S. Telford, 1940
F. T. Thwaites, 1941-42
William M. Tidd, 1939
Torrey Botanical Club, 1942
H. K. Townes, 1942
Lawrence D. Townsend, 1941
Willis L. Tressler, 1939, 1941
Ed Thatcher, 1941-42
Thomas G. Thompson, 1937-39
W. H. Twenhofel, 1939-40
U.S. Civil Service Commission, 1941
U.S. Government Printing Office, 1936, 1938-39
University of Indiana, 1941
University of Minnesota, 1940-42
University of Pennsylvania, 1942
University of Wisconsin, 1936, 1941
Henry Van der Shalie, 1942
W. A. Van Engel, 1941-42
John Van Oosten, 1942
J. Paul Visscher, 1942
Owen B. Weeks, 1942
George Wene, 1942
"Whip," 1938
D. D. Whitney, 1939
Williams and Wilkins Co., 1939
Eliot C. Williams, 1942
Dwight E. Wilson, 1941
John Wilson, 1942
L. L. Woodruff, 1942
Roy A. Waggener, 1941
Paul S. Welch, 1938, 1942
G. C. Wheeler, 1939, 1941
Ira T. Wilson, 1939, 1941
Yale University, 1940-41
Claude E. ZoBell, 1939
Ecology -- Minnesota; Science; Cedar Bog Lake (Minn.); Cedar Creek Bog (Minn.); Ecologists; Lindeman, Eleanor Hall; Lindeman, Raymond Laurel, 1915-1942
- Inventory, 1929-(1938-1942); 3.5 linear feet (10 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1939-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ackert, James E., 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ahlstrom, Elbert H., 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Midland Naturalist, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - B, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Buell, Murray C., 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - C, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Campbell, Robert S., 1939, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Carpenter, J. Richard, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cooper, William S., 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - D, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Deevey, Edward S., Jr., 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - E, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ecological Society of America, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ecology, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Eddy, Samuel, 1936-1937, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Eggleton, Frank E., 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - F, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - G, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Granovsky, A. A., 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - H, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Hooper, Frank, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hutchinson, G. Evelyn, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - I, 1939-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - J, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Juday, Chancey, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - K, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - L, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Lawrence, Donald, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - M, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Minnich, Dwight E., 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Moore, Walter G., 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - N, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - National Research Council, 1940, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - O, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - P, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Patrick, Ruth, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Prescott, G. W., 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - R, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Reif, Chuck, 1938-1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - S, 1938-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Sears, Paul B., 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - T, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Thatcher, Ed, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Thompson, Thomas G., 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Twenhofel, W. H., 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - U, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - V, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - W, 1938-1942 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Waggener, Roy A., 1941 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Welch, Paul S., 1938, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Wheeler, G. C., 1939, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Wilson, Ira T., 1939, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Yale University, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Z, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Unidentified, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Writings and research materials
    - "The Developmental History of Cedar Creek Bog,", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "Experimental Simulation of Winter Anaerobiosis,", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "Food Chain Dynamics in a Senescent Lake,", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Seasonal Distribution of Plants,", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - "Ecological Dynamics in a Senescent Lake, an abstract of a Ph.d. thesis by ...,", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "Seasonal Distribution of Midge Larvae,", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "Biological Productivity,", [1941?] (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - "Cedar Bog Lake: The Aquatic Community,", [1941?] (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "Cedar Bog Lake: The Physical and Chemical Environment,", [1941?] (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Fauna,", [1941?] (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "The Trophic Dynamic Aspect of Ecology (a series of working mss),", 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "Seasonal Food-Cycle Dynamics in a Senescent Lake,", [1942?] (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Pages from "Seasonal Food-Cycle Dynamics in a Senescent Lake,", [1942?] (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - "Regional Planktonic Diatom Studies in Minn.,", (undated) (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Unsorted rough drafts, notes, pages from articles, undated (Box 3, Folder 71-73)
    - Pencil diagrams, graphs and charts [from thesis?], undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Unidentified photographs of woods and pond, 1936-1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - County maps of Minnesota, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Brachionus plates by Jo Pickard, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Miscellaneous illustrations, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Notebooks
      - 1929, 1930s (Box 5–6)
      - [1930s?] (Box 7)
      - 1940-1942 (Box 8–9)
  - Miscellany
    - Quaternary Geology of Minnesota and Adjacent Regions, by Leverett and Sardeson, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Drawings [by Lindeman?], undated (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - "Physiology 23s - Laboratory Directors,", undated (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Miscellaneous practica, [1938?] (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - Eleanor (Hall) Lindeman
    - "Endocrine Glands and their Function,", 1938 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - English compositions, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Drawings, [1938?] (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Laboratory plates, undated (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Ornithology notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 87)